<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-20T19:51:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Kim Tom Can</title><subtitle>Kim Tom Can - Online Portfolio. Web Design &amp; Development, Graphic Design.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Passport Renewal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/passport-renewal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Passport Renewal" /><published>2018-07-20T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-20T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/passport-renewal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/passport-renewal">&lt;p&gt;Kamakailan, ang bisa ng pasaporte ng Pilipinas ay tumaas sa 10 taon mula sa dating limang taon lamang. Dahil siguro rito, at dahil na rin nagiging mas abot-kaya ang pagbili ng tiket sa eroplano, salamat sa mga budget airline, at nauuso ang paglalakbay sa ibang bansa, dumami ang mga nagpapa-renew ng kani-kanilang pasaporte.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;appointment&quot;&gt;Appointment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upang makapagpa-renew ng pasaporte, kailangan munang makakuha ng appointment sa DFA. Maaari itong gawin sa pamamagitan ng pagpunta sa website ng DFA, o &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.passport.gov.ph/appointment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;i-click ang link na ito&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bago pa man magpatuloy, mabuting ihanda ang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pasaporte&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;email address&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;buong pangalan ng mga magulang (at kung mayroon, asawa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piliin kung saang branch ng DFA ang kayang puntahan. Makikita kung may bakanteng slot para makapagpa-schedule ng appointment. Kung walang makitang available slot, subukan uli sa susunod. Kung may makitang available slot, punan ang mga hihingin na impormasyon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayroon kang 15 minuto para tapusin ang proseso ng pagkuha ng appointment. Kung lumampas sa 15 minuto, at wala pang ibang nakakuha ng slot, maaaring subukan muli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paano malalaman kung naireserba para sa’yo ang appointment schedule? May matatanggap dapat na confirmation email sa email address na nilagay sa form. Pag nakuha ito, i-click agad ang confirmation link para masiguradong nakuha mo nga ang appointment. Kailangang ma-click ang link na ito sa loob ng isang oras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paano kung walang natanggap na email?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maaaring napunta ito sa spam folder o iba pang folder (sa Gmail, maaaring mapunta ito sa Updates folder) ng iyong email.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maaaring mali ang nailagay na email address.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maaaring hindi pumasok sa sistema ng DFA ang inyong request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;payment&quot;&gt;Payment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kapag sa DFA Manila (ASEANA) ang kinuhang appointment, kailangang magbayad muna bago masiguradong sa iyo mapupunta ang slot. Sa ibang branch ng DFA, sa mismong araw na ng appointment ito babayaran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maghanda ng Php950.00 para sa regular na pagpoproseso; Php1,200.00 naman kung nais ipa-rush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ang sabi sa website ng DFA ay makukuha na ang pasaporte pagkatapos ng 15 working days (7 kung rush) pero sa DFA Baguio, sa kaso ko ay aabot ng 20 working days. Tignan ang mga nakapaskil sa opisina ng DFA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ang kailangan lang dalhin sa inyong appointment ay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ang print-out ng application form na ipapadala ng DFA sa inyong email (dalawang pahina ito: ang isa ay checklist na kung saan ay nakasulat din ang araw at oras ng inyong appointment; ang isa pa ay ang mismong application form)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ang inyong pasaporte&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;photocopy ng pasaporte (iyong pahina na may litrato, pangalan, at iba pang detalye)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kung hindi pa pinagbayad ng processing fee, siguraduhin na ring may dalang sapat na kwarta para rito.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mangyari na ring siguraduhin kung may kailangang dalhing karagdagang dokumento sa &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dfa.gov.ph/100-passport-information/246-renewal-of-passport-requirements&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;website ng DFA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;renewal&quot;&gt;Renewal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainam na pumunta sa DFA nang mas maaga sa oras ng inyong appointment. Sa kaso ko, 3PM-4PM ang appointment ko. Dumating ako ng mga 2:45PM at pinapasok naman na ako.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ang unang ginawa ay sinigurado sa front desk na sapat ang dalang rekisito para sa renewal. Sumunod ay ang pagbayad ng processing fee. Pagkatapos ay kukunan ng litrato, finger prints, at lagda. Ibabalik ang pasaporte kasama ang resibo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inabot ako ng isang oras sa DFA. Pinakanagtagal sa pagkuha ng litrato, finger prints, at lagda.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Philippines" /><category term="adulting" /><category term="Philippines" /><category term="documents" /><category term="DFA" /><category term="passport" /><category term="life" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Kamakailan, ang bisa ng pasaporte ng Pilipinas ay tumaas sa 10 taon mula sa dating limang taon lamang. Dahil siguro rito, at dahil na rin nagiging mas abot-kaya ang pagbili ng tiket sa eroplano, salamat sa mga budget airline, at nauuso ang paglalakbay sa ibang bansa, dumami ang mga nagpapa-renew ng kani-kanilang pasaporte.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ensoku 遠足</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/ensoku" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ensoku 遠足" /><published>2018-07-13T20:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-07-13T20:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/ensoku</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/ensoku">&lt;p&gt;We had our field trip (遠足) on a Friday in June. I had been thinking of starting a vlog, so I thought I would start by making a video of this experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;yt-embed-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/F0Q_Q_k1uyw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Amazon, I bought a gimbal for my phone, a microphone, and an attachment that I can put on the gimbal to hold the microphone. I also bought neutral density filters from Yodobashi Camera because I had no control of my phone’s aperture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/vidgear.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vlog Gear&quot; title=&quot;gimbal, microphone, attachment&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally intended to take statements from the other students, but the way my phone was setup on the gimbal didn’t leave enough room to connect the mic to my phone. Also forgot to remove the ND filter when the room got dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought two other cameras with me. Barely used one, and didn’t even take the other out of my bag. Taking videos takes up quite a lot of one’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me two days to edit the video. I showed it to my teachers. They liked it; showed it to other school staff. They told me the people in charge of publicity/marketing liked the video, and asked me if it would be alright with me if they uploaded the video to Facebook and YouTube. (The video above was uploaded under the ISI Language School account.) I agreed without really asking for acknowledgment or pay because I felt the content was bland. It wasn’t something I would want to include in my YouTube Channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went to the Ninjutsu Village 忍術村, Nagahama Black Wall Square 長浜黒壁スクエア, and Nagahama Castle 長浜城. It was mostly just sight-seeing. Once we got to a destination, there would be a group photo, and then we could go off on our own and just come back to the bus before it leaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some activities in the Ninjutsu Village, but there wasn’t really enough time to go around the entire place and enjoy yourself, unless maybe you move quickly through everything. At the Black Wall Square, it was mostly shops. Only a few of us went to the nearby shrine. There was even less time to go around the castle grounds of Nakahama Castle because they were about to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was nothing much to the field trip itself. It rained a bit now and then. It was hot and humid. The school istn’t really very good at organizing events (and making them interesting). Anyway, we were still able to enjoy the company of friends, and see our teachers in a slightly different light.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="ISI" /><category term="Kyoto" /><category term="travel" /><category term="video" /><summary type="html">We had our field trip (遠足) on a Friday in June. I had been thinking of starting a vlog, so I thought I would start by making a video of this experience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part V: Transportation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-5-transportation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part V: Transportation" /><published>2018-05-31T19:15:30+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-31T19:15:30+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-5-transportation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-5-transportation">&lt;h2 id=&quot;public-transportation&quot;&gt;Public Transportation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kyoto isn’t as busy as Tokyo or Osaka, so trains and buses don’t have as many trips. Intervals between trips are usually longer than 10 minutes, and sometimes that’s what makes you’re commute time longer. In the late evenings, there are even less trips per hour. When I was still working at an izakaya, it would take me about 35 minutes to go from my dorm to work by train, and roughly twice that on my way home using the same route.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only a few train lines in Kyoto. Buses tend to have a wider reach than trains. However, if you do intend to go to tourist spots around Kyoto, you can be sure that there is at least one train station or bus stop around the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trains and buses seldom get crowded. When they do, it’s usually because of tourists. I have been in one or two buses that couldn’t take in any more passengers, usually after going through popular tourist spots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trains&quot;&gt;Trains&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only a few train lines operating in Kyoto, making it much easier to navigate the train system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Keifuku trams have a fixed rate of 220円 per trip. You pay on the train, before exiting, unless you get off at the last station, in which payment would be at the station gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/randen-keifuku.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Keifuku Randen tram&quot; title=&quot;Keifuku Randen tram&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there are JR lines, but they can only take you to very limited areas within Kyoto. My school and dorm are both near JR train stations, so commuting by train is really convenient. Other than commuting to and from school, the only other times I use the JR train lines are when I travel outside Kyoto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also other private lines in Kyoto. Some of them may be cheaper than JR, but like JR, they can only take you to limited places around the prefecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buses&quot;&gt;Buses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Kyoto, buses with routes that go around Kyoto City have a fixed rate of 230円. There is also a bus route that is only 100円, though I’ve never had to use it, but often see it around town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there aren’t any train stations nearby, there are most likely bus stops around. Bus stops also aren’t too far from each other. Each route has several bus stops, and it’s pretty rare to go 5minutes without stopping at a bus stop. There is some traffic around town, but it’s not terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to take the bus more often, but there have been a number of times when the bus arrives later or doesn’t arrive at all (based on the printed schedule, and Google Maps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have also been some cases where there are several bus stops in an area, and I’ve had to go back and forth trying to figure out which bus stop the bus I wanted to get on was going to stop at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commuter-pass-定期券&quot;&gt;Commuter Pass (定期券)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can purchase a commuter pass (teikiken) for the JR line, and for fixed-fare buses. The commuter pass comes as an ICOCA card with details of your pass (your name, route, the validity of your pass, etc.) printed on it. Because it’s an ICOCA card, there’s a 500円 deposit. If you already have an ICOCA card, you can use that for your commuter pass so you don’t have to keep getting a new card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the JR line, the amout you pay for depends on your commute route, i.e. from what station to what station. For the bus commuter pass, the price depends on distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the commute route on your commuter pass, you can still use your commuter pass to travel outside your route. Say your commuter pass is only for station S1 to S4, but you’re taking the train from S2 to S5, you will only be charged the fare from S4 to S5 (as if you took the train only from S4 to S5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get your commuter pass from Kyoto station. There are also some JR stations with green ticket vending machines. You can purchase commuter passes from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask your school if they can give you a student commuter pass, as it is cheaper than regular commuter passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bicycles&quot;&gt;Bicycles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheapest way to get around Kyoto is by bike. Especially if you’re planning to stay long-term. If you’re lucky, you can buy a second-hand bike for less than 10,000円 from Sayonara Sales, but do make sure to get proper registration. Bike theft does happen in Japan, so getting the proper papers from your seller ensures that what you’re buying isn’t stolen property. And if your bike does happen to get stolen, the police can easily identify your bike and help you find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided against buying a bicycle because I was only supposed to study in Kyoto from October to March, and I didn’t want to ride a bicycle out in the cold. It hardly snowed this year (and it doesn’t snow that much in Kyoto city), so that’s something you don’t have to worry much about if you’re thinking about buying a bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a free bike parking right outside &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my school&lt;/a&gt; and that could have saved me a lot of money. And speaking of parking, be mindful of places where you can and can’t park your bicycle. There are usually spaces in front of stores (especially convenience stores and supermarkets) where you can park your bike. You can also look for bicycle parking signs (駐輪場).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also be mindful of where you can and can’t ride your bike. There are some sidewalks where you can’t ride your bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxis-and-uber&quot;&gt;Taxis and… Uber?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buses and trains only operate up to a certain time, so if you’re out until 1a.m. and you don’t have a bike, you either have to wait until the trains and buses are back in operation (which is around 5a.m.), or you can take a taxi, or an Uber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxis throughout Japan are expensive. I mostly see taxis pass along major roads, so hailing a taxi from a residential area away from main roads is probably going to be challenging. If you have Internet connection, you can hail taxis through apps. You can also call taxi companies by phone to come and pick you up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my housemates usually uses Uber when he comes home in the early mornings. He says it’s cheaper than taxis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="budget" /><category term="transportation" /><category term="commute" /><category term="train" /><category term="bus" /><category term="Kyoto" /><summary type="html">Public Transportation Kyoto isn’t as busy as Tokyo or Osaka, so trains and buses don’t have as many trips. Intervals between trips are usually longer than 10 minutes, and sometimes that’s what makes you’re commute time longer. In the late evenings, there are even less trips per hour. When I was still working at an izakaya, it would take me about 35 minutes to go from my dorm to work by train, and roughly twice that on my way home using the same route.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Guide to Touring Kyoto</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/tmp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Guide to Touring Kyoto" /><published>2018-05-26T17:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-26T17:10:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/tmp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/tmp"></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="travel" /><category term="Japanese" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="personal" /><category term="isi" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Guide to Touring Kyoto</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/a-guide-to-touring-kyoto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Guide to Touring Kyoto" /><published>2018-05-10T17:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-10T17:10:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/a-guide-to-touring-kyoto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/a-guide-to-touring-kyoto">&lt;p&gt;Filipinos usually allot only a few days for travelling (because we don’t want to use up all our paid vacation leaves in one go). When we do travel, especially abroad, we want to make the most of it, i.e., doing as much sight-seeing as you possibly can. To do that, it’s best to have an itinerary. Not necessarily something you need to follow down to the letter, but at least something to refer to so you know where to go and how to get there (and if you’re on a budget, how much it would cost).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re making your own itinerary, here are a few points I advise you to consider:
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-transportation-in-kyoto-has-its-limitations&quot;&gt;1. Transportation in Kyoto has its limitations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trains can only take you to limited places, and the intervals between trips are usually longer than 10 minutes. Getting day passes for trains also doesn’t seem to be worth it as they won’t be able to take you to all the tourist spots anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buses are a better way to get around and tour the city. As far as I know, every popular tourist spot in Kyoto has a nearby bus stop. Taking the bus can also be cheaper than taking the train. Buses that go around within Kyoto City (not the entire prefecture) have a fixed price of JPY230 (JPY120 for kids). A day pass as of posting is JPY600 (used to be just JPY500).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just like trains, intervals between bus trips can take longer than 10 minutes. But there are usually more than one bus route you can take to go from point A to point B. The downside of taking the bus, though, is that sometimes they arrive late or not at all, and you have no way of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-most-tourist-spots-involve-a-lot-of-walking-or-hiking&quot;&gt;2. Most tourist spots involve a lot of walking or hiking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sight-seeing in Kyoto is mostly walking around and taking in the surroundings. If you’re not used to walking, you might have to take breaks now and then, which you might want to consider in planning your itinerary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-most-toursit-spots-close-by-5pm&quot;&gt;3. Most toursit spots close by 5PM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I found to be most challenging when I plan itineraries for people I show around Kyoto. Aside from the time it takes to walk to/around tourist spots, and the not-so-frequent bus trips, that most tourist spots close by 5PM (some even earlier) makes it harder to fit more places to visit in one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re visiting mid-Autumn or during Sakura season, there might be some tourist spots with Illumination events that will allow you to visit at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BhDLskgHeCF/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-tourists-everywhere&quot;&gt;4. Tourists everywhere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical tourist destinations start getting crowded from 10AM. Crowds usually gather by the entrance, mostly because they’re excited to take pictures and selfies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-go-what-to-see&quot;&gt;Where to go, What to see&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to visit as many (popular tourist) places as you can within two or three days (one day is really not enough), the best way to go about it is to divide the city into three: west, middle, and east. In this way, you don’t spend too much time going from one place to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/kyoto-map-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto City&quot; title=&quot;Kyoto Map: West, Center, East&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve listed the popular places to visit and a couple not-so-popular places as well. You can visit 2 places in the morning; another 1 or 2 after lunch, before 5PM; and at night, if you’re into it, you can go to Shijo, or Gion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;west-kyoto&quot;&gt;West Kyoto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arashiyama Bamboo Forest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arashiyama Monkey Park&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toei Kyoto Studio Park&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/kyoto-west.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto City - West&quot; title=&quot;Kyoto Map: West&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;arashiyama-bamboo-forest&quot;&gt;Arashiyama Bamboo Forest&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arashiyama Bamboo Forest doesn’t have an opening or closing time (and admission is free), so this is a good place to start (or end) your day. You can avoid a huge crowd if you come before 10AM or after 4PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arashiyama-bamboo-crowd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Crowded Arashiyama Bamboo Forest&quot; title=&quot;Crowded Arashiyama Bamboo Forest&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/kimtomshoots/albums/72157661159765997&quot; title=&quot;Arashiyama&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4559/24894511708_a490da351b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;212&quot; alt=&quot;Arashiyama&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bamboo Forest branches into different paths. There are temples nearby. There is also a path that can take you to &lt;strong&gt;Katsura River&lt;/strong&gt;, across which is the Arashiyama Monkey Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;arashiyama-monkey-park&quot;&gt;Arashiyama Monkey Park&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 9AM - 4PM. Admission is JPY550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/kimtomshoots/27143359127/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Monkey Park&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/905/27143359127_949c3074d4_z.jpg&quot; width=&quot;320&quot; height=&quot;212&quot; alt=&quot;Monkey Park&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a (roughly) 20-minute hike to get to the monkeys. Along the path, there are some trivia about the macaque monkeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;toei-kyoto-studio-park&quot;&gt;Toei Kyoto Studio Park&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 9AM - 5PM. Admission is JPY2,200 for adults; some attractions cost additional fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bhiw8-BB1xt/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Toei Kyoto Studio Park is a film set and theme park that recreates the Edo Period. There are some shows you can watch for free. There are also some actors roaming around the park with whom you can take pictures with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;middle-kyoto&quot;&gt;Middle Kyoto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nijo Castle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kyoto International Manga Museum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imperial Palace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kinkaku-ji (Golden Pavilion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/kyoto-center.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto City - Center&quot; title=&quot;Kyoto Map: Center&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nijo-castle&quot;&gt;Nijo Castle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 8:45AM - 5PM, but admission is only up to 4PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BfGLdFJnzJH/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BilXpRehSUZ/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kyoto-international-manga-museum&quot;&gt;Kyoto International Manga Museum&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 10AM - 6PM, entry up to 5:30PM. Closed on Wednesdays. Admission is JPY800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a library of manga inside. Before the entrance there’s a shop for merch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;imperial-palace&quot;&gt;Imperial Palace&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 9AM ~ 4PM. Closed on Mondays. There may be additional days when they are closed. Admission is free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/9fFUAZj72j/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kyoto Imperial Park is really, really spacious. Aside from the Imperial Palace, there is another palace inside the park. If it happens that you visit the Imperial Park on a day (or time) when the Palace itself is closed, there will still be a lot for you to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kinkaku-ji-golden-pavilion&quot;&gt;Kinkaku-ji (Golden Pavilion)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 9AM - 5PM. Admission is JPY400.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BiluKBGBa03/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to get here is by bus, as there are no train stations nearby. Do prepare yourself to ride a crowded bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;east-kyoto&quot;&gt;East Kyoto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fushimi-inari&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kiyomizu-dera&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ginkaku-ji  (Silver Pavilion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/kyoto-east.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto City - East&quot; title=&quot;Kyoto Map: East&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fushimi-inari&quot;&gt;Fushimi-inari&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fushimi-inari, like Arashiyama Bamboo Forest, also has no opening or closing hours and no admission fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BbBL6ReHSxo/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gets really crowded in the first two sets of torii (the red Shinto shrine archways), but the deeper you go into the mountain, the less crowded it gets, the less people you will be in the way of while you’re taking pictures, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BbEwU-cH5Vw/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to hike all the way to the top, especially if you’re following a schedule. There isn’t much to see up there. Personally, it didn’t feel as rewarding as I thought it would (but I did enjoy the time I spent with my friends getting there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fushimi-inari is along the JR Nara Line, so if you’re planning to go to Uji and/or Nara as well, you might want to take this into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kiyomizu-dera&quot;&gt;Kiyomizu-dera&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 6AM - 6PM. There is a part of Kiyomizu-dera that has an entrance fee of JPY400.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BgqyKlaHKpq/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to Kiyomizu-dera, you will have to walk up a hill lined with souvenir shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ginkaku-ji-silver-pavilion&quot;&gt;Ginkaku-ji (Silver Pavilion)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open from 8:30AM ~ 4:30PM. Admission is JPY500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found Ginkaku-ji to be more memorable than Kinkaku-ji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/9iiYc0j7xi/&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;8&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bb4aEZpnRdO/&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Kim Cantillas (@kimtillas)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-11-24T14:29:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Nov 24, 2017 at 6:29am PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigation&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Maps&lt;/strong&gt; is a good-enough app to use for navigation around Kyoto, but it’s not always accurate. Sometimes it pins a bus stop at the center of an intersection. But, if you can’t read Japanese, Google Maps is very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can read Japanese, &lt;strong&gt;Y! MAP&lt;/strong&gt; is more accurate and has more detailed information (and has a sorting criterion for cheapest path).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re taking the bus, make sure you’re on the right side of the road. The Japanese are usually very helpful. If you don’t want to bother someone randomly on the street, you can ask the bus driver if you’re getting on the right bus.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="travel" /><category term="guide" /><category term="Kyoto" /><category term="tour" /><summary type="html">Filipinos usually allot only a few days for travelling (because we don’t want to use up all our paid vacation leaves in one go). When we do travel, especially abroad, we want to make the most of it, i.e., doing as much sight-seeing as you possibly can. To do that, it’s best to have an itinerary. Not necessarily something you need to follow down to the letter, but at least something to refer to so you know where to go and how to get there (and if you’re on a budget, how much it would cost). If you’re making your own itinerary, here are a few points I advise you to consider:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Quit My Baito</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/i-quit-my-baito" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Quit My Baito" /><published>2018-03-30T20:45:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T20:45:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/i-quit-my-baito</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/i-quit-my-baito">&lt;p&gt;Living in Japan, even as a student, is quite expensive. Prices of goods and services are relatively expensive, even with discounts for food and transportation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before coming to Kyoto, I was already looking for part-time work I could start applying for. I didn’t anticipate, though, how difficult it would be to find a job that would also allow me to practice Japanese with the level I was at (N4). Most jobs where you get to be exposed to language require at least N3 (daily conversation) level. Even English-teaching jobs are difficult to find for non-Native speakers.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
When I arrived in Kyoto, my school had only been operating for 3 months, so during my first term, the available jobs posted on our bulletin board were more of factory work and cleaning jobs. And although I was fine with that kind of work, .the hiring organization that was working with the school never got back to me about the jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I looked for other means to find jobs. My sister’s friend introduced me to her friend, who introduced me to another friend who got me an interview at the restaurant she worked at. Unfortunately I failed that interview because half-way into the interview, I choked because my interviewer started using words I wasn’t yet familiar with. I also found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hello-sensei.com/en/sensei&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;website for connecting language learners to teachers&lt;/a&gt;, but no one ever contacted me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then started seeing ads on Facebook for services that help foreigners find work in Japan. I first tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://findworks.jp/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;FindWorks&lt;/a&gt; and they introduced me to what would be my first part-time job. It was a popular izakaya chain. I passed the interview, but because I was too focused on just getting employed, I didn’t think carefully about the conditions that would eventually be part of the reasons why I quit that job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get to why I quit, I also want to express my frustration in the application process. After passing the interview, I was asked to submit some documents (from my school and the ward office) which cost me a significant amount of money—maybe a few hundred to a thousand yen. After submitting the documents, I had to wait for the regional office to deliver the shoes that was part of our uniform, and that took about a month. During that waiting period, the good people from FindWorks kept asking for updates about my application, so I had to keep calling the izakaya/regional office for updates. And for someone who doesn’t like making phone calls, having to make phone calls in a language you’re still just learning caused a lot of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really pushed me to quit was the branch manager. It’s not that he would embarass me in front of other people, but he made me feel like my inadequacies were all completely my fault, even though the training they gave me wasn’t nearly sufficient. It was also in the way he talked down on me, and how unreasonable he was. (I called in sick and he told me to go all the way to the izakaya to have the assistant manager “confirm” that I was sick, instead of just having me call the assistant manager instead. It was winter.) And every time I had work, I always felt a creeping anxiety before my shift started, which I suspect was because of the branch manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from how terrible I felt about the branch manager, two other major problems I had with the job were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I couldn’t work as much as I wanted to.&lt;/strong&gt; My manager would only give me very limited working hours per week. Sometimes just one 4-hour shift a week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wasn’t allowed to work outside the group of companies the izakaya belonged to.&lt;/strong&gt; So I basically wasn’t allowed to find another work to compensate for the measley number of hours I was being given. (I didn’t want to work for other restaurants under the same company because of my experience with them.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have trouble quitting, though. It took maybe just a minute for me to tell the branch manager about it, and he was pretty satisfied with my reason for quitting being school-related. (He wasn’t really a bad person, just didn’t have the type of leadership I agree with.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group of companies required a specific bank in which they would deposit the salary, but I wasn’t able to open an account at that bank because they have a requirement where you have to have already lived in Japan for 6 months before you could open an account with them. During my interview, they told me that I had to go all the way to the regional office in Osaka to get my salary, but a couple of weeks after my last day, the branch manager told me to come to the izakaya to come and get my salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The school has recently been in contact with more establishments, so there are more options for employment. It was the school that introduced me to my current job, also a restaurant. My boss is great; she’s like a mom. And the people leading don’t expect you to know everything. If they know you aren’t ready to do something, they won’t force you, but they will encourage and push you to take more and more responsibility until you get used to the work. I also had to come in late one day (because I was moving out and my schedule got pushed back by two hours) and my boss was very understanding about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes my working days change though, like if someone asks to have their schedule changed and my boss has to re-adjust other people’s schedules as well, because you can’t have too many or too few on staff. But I still get at at least 20 hours a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both my part-time jobs were at restaurants and it’s been a real eye-opener to be in the service industry. During peak hours it gets really tiring. Even a four-hour shift can be exhausting, whether you’re just washing dishes, or preparing food, or serving customers. It always feels good when a customer is polite, and more so when they express their appreciation for your service.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="personal" /><category term="adulting" /><category term="work" /><summary type="html">Living in Japan, even as a student, is quite expensive. Prices of goods and services are relatively expensive, even with discounts for food and transportation. Even before coming to Kyoto, I was already looking for part-time work I could start applying for. I didn’t anticipate, though, how difficult it would be to find a job that would also allow me to practice Japanese with the level I was at (N4). Most jobs where you get to be exposed to language require at least N3 (daily conversation) level. Even English-teaching jobs are difficult to find for non-Native speakers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part IV: Accommodation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-4-accommodations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part IV: Accommodation" /><published>2018-03-13T23:15:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-03-13T23:15:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-4-accommodations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-4-accommodations">&lt;p&gt;After finally securing your application to a language school, you now have to think about accommodations. If you applied to a language school via a service such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://gogonihon.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Go! Go! Nihon&lt;/a&gt;, they usually help you find accommodations. Your options usually include dormitories, apartments, sharehouses, and homestays. If you applied directly to a school, they would also likely help you find a place. After all, they sponsored your visa, so they are in some way responsible for you. You can also look for a place on your own via the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something you may want to consider is that whenever you rent, there are usually one-time fees you have to pay which can’t be refunded. So if you want to save some money, it’s best not to keep moving around. Also, everytime you change your address, you will have to go to the ward office (区役所) to have your Residence Card updated.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dormitories&quot;&gt;Dormitories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dormitories are relatively more affordable than others, but they aren’t all cheap. The dormitory I stayed at (around Arashiyama) increased the fees by 2,000円 last January, and will be increasing the rent by another 2,000円 next month. The increase in price brings it close to the amount I am paying now to stay at a sharehouse, in which I now have a room of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design, management and maintenance of dormitories varies. In the case of my dormitory, everyone staying there is from the same school. Each room has two tenants. Boys stay on the first floor; girls on the second floor. The management provides tissue, cleaning materials, cooking utensils (pots, pans, knives, chopping boards). Someone also comes in thrice a week to clean the common areas. You have to pay to use the washing machine and clothes dryer. The showers and toilets are shared (one shower room and one room for toilets per floor). The kitchen is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the worst part of staying in such a dorm is having to stay with people who aren’t mature enough to live in a space where they have to share with other people. Some of the people in my dorm don’t wash the dishes and utensils they used. They leave the kitchen messy almost every night. There was also someone who got one of the toilets clogged and didn’t bother telling the management (or at least the school) about it, so it took maybe a week before we could use that toilet again. And most recently, someone supposedly took a dump in the shower and left it there. (I didn’t actually see the poop, but the management posted a sign on the shower room door asking to not take a dump in the showers — they are very passive-aggressive when dealing with the tenants.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are some dorms wherein you already have a kitchen and bathroom in your room. These are likely more expensive. Some dorms aren’t necessarily affiliated with or owned by schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;apartments&quot;&gt;Apartments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Japan, an apartment is usually called a “mansion”. Apartments come in different shapes and sizes. A common acronym you might see while searching for a place to rent is “LDK”, which stands for Living, Dining, Kitchen. There is usually a number in front of it, which indicates the number of bedrooms there are. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gaijinpot.com/what-do-japanese-apartment-layout-terms-mean/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;read more about layouts here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the people I know renting apartments, only one of them is lives by herself. It’s much more affordable if you can split rent with friends (if you happen to be coming to Japan with any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing is that some apartments don’t provide Internet connection, so you would have to get it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharehouses&quot;&gt;ShareHouses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharehouses are typically slightly more expensive than dormitories. Most would probably be around 60,000円 a month including utilities and WiFi. Sharehouses are also popular among Japanese people, so there’s a good chance that you will be able to live with Japanese people and maybe, if your schedules align, be able to interact with them and even make friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some sharehouses that regulate how many foreigners and locals can stay in the sharehouse at a time. That’s actually how it is here where I am staying now. They also have a lot of other perks that you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borderless-house.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;check on their website&lt;/a&gt;. They also offer a discount for students!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison with the dorm, though, you typically have more responsibilities in a sharehouse. Everyone is expected to pitch in with chores. Some sharehouses do have someone come in maybe once a week to clean up some of the common areas. One such sharehouse is &lt;a href=&quot;https://kansai.hituji.jp/comret/info/kyoto/kyoto/rakuran/special/2515&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Raku Arashi (楽嵐)&lt;/a&gt;. It’s owned by a really nice couple, and because it isn’t owned by a group or company, you can negotiate with the owners if the price is too expensive. It’s an all-girl sharehouse, each room having it’s own theme. There’s also a TV inside each room, so if you’re a very private person, this might be a good choice for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;airbnb&quot;&gt;AirBnb&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found out from one of my friends that it is possible to rent long-term through AirBNB. The good thing about AirBNB is that you don’t have to pay for the usual one-time fees when renting a dorm, apartment, or sharehouse. As far as I’ve searched, the price of the AirBNB doesn’t stray so far from the price of other accommodation types. However, you do have more limited options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t satisfied with the available accommodation options, you can temporarily stay at an AirBNB while searching or waiting for something better. For most accommodations, only a 1-month advance notice is necessary before moving out, so by the time you arrive in Japan, there might be more options available to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homestay&quot;&gt;Homestay&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most expensive option is the homestay. I’m not so sure about arrangements with homestays, like how long you can stay with one family and things like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.borderless-house.com/program/homestay/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Borderless House&lt;/a&gt; actually has a short (3 days, 2 nights) homestay program if it’s something you really want to experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="personal" /><category term="budget" /><category term="accommodation" /><category term="Kyoto" /><summary type="html">After finally securing your application to a language school, you now have to think about accommodations. If you applied to a language school via a service such as Go! Go! Nihon, they usually help you find accommodations. Your options usually include dormitories, apartments, sharehouses, and homestays. If you applied directly to a school, they would also likely help you find a place. After all, they sponsored your visa, so they are in some way responsible for you. You can also look for a place on your own via the Internet. Something you may want to consider is that whenever you rent, there are usually one-time fees you have to pay which can’t be refunded. So if you want to save some money, it’s best not to keep moving around. Also, everytime you change your address, you will have to go to the ward office (区役所) to have your Residence Card updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learn Japanese: Getting Started</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/learn-japanese-getting-started" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learn Japanese: Getting Started" /><published>2018-03-07T18:25:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-03-07T18:25:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/learn-japanese-getting-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/learn-japanese-getting-started">&lt;p&gt;Back in highschool, almost all my friends loved anime. I didn’t watch as much as they did, but I started getting hooked and watched mostly what my friends also watched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In anime, they make Japanese sound really cool (I’m not a fan of dubbing). If you watch anime often, you pick up words and phrases and feel like you’re slowly starting to learn the language. And so you think, why not learn Nihongo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nihongo-日本語&quot;&gt;Nihongo 日本語&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, I think it would be helpful to paint a picture of Japanese (from here on I shall refer to as ‘Nihongo’) as a language.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;grammatical-structure&quot;&gt;Grammatical Structure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic word order of English is &lt;strong&gt;SVO&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that the &lt;strong&gt;Subject&lt;/strong&gt; comes first, then the &lt;strong&gt;Verb&lt;/strong&gt;, then the &lt;strong&gt;Object&lt;/strong&gt; of the Verb. For Nihongo, however, it’s &lt;strong&gt;SOV&lt;/strong&gt;, so the &lt;strong&gt;Verb&lt;/strong&gt; comes last. (And in my native language, Tagalog, it’s &lt;strong&gt;VSO&lt;/strong&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m bilingual, fluent in two languages with different structures, but I still found it difficult to learn and get used to the word order of Nihongo. It takes a lot of getting used to, but if you practice thinking in the language you are learning as often as you can, constructing your own sentences, you will eventually get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, thinking in Japanese is like staging a play. Set the stage and placing the actors and objects, and then giving the actors direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-system&quot;&gt;Writing System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nihongo uses three sets of characters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiragana (ひらがな)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katakana (カタカナ)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kanji (漢字)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kanji are characters borrowed from the Chinese, some of which were made in Japan. Hiragana and Katakana are also based on Kanji, each character representing a single syllable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start studying Nihongo, the most important to learn is Hiragana. There are several Hiragana charts you can scour on the Internet. I suggest learning the proper stroke order as well. It can help make your writing more legible, as well as recognize other fonts and hand-writing. Once you’ve learned Hiragana, as much as possible, try not to write Nihongo in Romaji (Roman characters).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katakana is typically used for words borrowed from other languages, and onomatopoeia. After learning Hiragana, Katakana should be easy. (Hiragana and Katakana are collectively called “Kana”.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Kanji, if you’re still starting out, it’s something you can learn as you go along. If there are words you are particularly interested, you can look up the Kanji on your own. You can also look for resources with a suggested sequence of Kanji for you to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resources below are meant as supplementary materials. I can’t really recommend any one book or app as your main resource for self-studying Nihongo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While studying Basic Nihongo, I was able to use two different books: Genki and Minna no Nihongo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I studied Nihongo in a Japanese Language School at my hometown, we used &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2tr1iMG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Minna no Nihongo&lt;/a&gt;. In another school (not a language school), we used Genki. Personally, I didn’t like Genki. I felt it was too…talkative, with longer-than-necessary explanations in English that I didn’t find particularly helpful, and not nearly enough example sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;adspace&quot;&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
amzn_assoc_placement = &quot;adunit0&quot;;
amzn_assoc_tracking_id = &quot;kimtomcan-20&quot;;
amzn_assoc_ad_mode = &quot;search&quot;;
amzn_assoc_ad_type = &quot;smart&quot;;
amzn_assoc_marketplace = &quot;amazon&quot;;
amzn_assoc_region = &quot;US&quot;;
amzn_assoc_default_search_phrase = &quot;minna no nihongo&quot;;
amzn_assoc_default_category = &quot;All&quot;;
amzn_assoc_linkid = &quot;985951b4979d3f6de73ecef04b677157&quot;;
amzn_assoc_design = &quot;in_content&quot;;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;//z-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/onejs?MarketPlace=US&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Japan, our language school also uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2FpEaiM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Minna no Nihongo&lt;/a&gt; for its Basic Level Academic course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get yourself accustomed to the language, practice the grammar and vocabulary you’ve learned, and eaven learn how to construct better sentences, I suggest reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2G5cfpO&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Tadoku Books&lt;/a&gt;. The point of Tadoku is to read a lot. You can start with familiar stories translated to Nihongo to get accustomed to narrative styles in Nihongo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youtube-videos--channels&quot;&gt;YouTube Videos / Channels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;nihongo-dekimasu&quot;&gt;Nihongo Dekimasu&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find playlists for Nihongo Dekimasu on YouTube. The series follows an exchange student as she learns to use different grammar patterns with the help of an anthropomorphized duck, and a robot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nihongo-de-kurasou&quot;&gt;Nihongo de Kurasou&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nihongo de Kurasou also shows different situations where you can use different grammar patterns, but is geared towards adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;japanese-from-zero--japanese-in-5&quot;&gt;Japanese from Zero / Japanese in 5&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japanese from Zero and Japanese in 5 are both from the same YouTuber, George. He’s an American who went to Japan as a teenager (if I’m not mistaken), worked as a translator/interpreter, and now teaches Nihongo in America. He has his own website that also has a community of Nihongo learners. He also wrote a series of books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;adspace&quot;&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
amzn_assoc_placement = &quot;adunit0&quot;;
amzn_assoc_tracking_id = &quot;kimtomcan-20&quot;;
amzn_assoc_ad_mode = &quot;search&quot;;
amzn_assoc_ad_type = &quot;smart&quot;;
amzn_assoc_marketplace = &quot;amazon&quot;;
amzn_assoc_region = &quot;US&quot;;
amzn_assoc_default_search_phrase = &quot;japanese from zero&quot;;
amzn_assoc_default_category = &quot;All&quot;;
amzn_assoc_linkid = &quot;985951b4979d3f6de73ecef04b677157&quot;;
amzn_assoc_design = &quot;in_content&quot;;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;//z-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/onejs?MarketPlace=US&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of suggested apps, click &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/apps-to-supplement-your-nihongo-study&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="learn" /><category term="Japanese" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="books" /><summary type="html">Back in highschool, almost all my friends loved anime. I didn’t watch as much as they did, but I started getting hooked and watched mostly what my friends also watched. In anime, they make Japanese sound really cool (I’m not a fan of dubbing). If you watch anime often, you pick up words and phrases and feel like you’re slowly starting to learn the language. And so you think, why not learn Nihongo? Nihongo 日本語 To start, I think it would be helpful to paint a picture of Japanese (from here on I shall refer to as ‘Nihongo’) as a language.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Apps to Supplement Your Nihongo Study</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/apps-to-supplement-your-nihongo-study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apps to Supplement Your Nihongo Study" /><published>2018-02-17T13:24:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-02-17T13:24:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/apps-to-supplement-your-nihongo-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/apps-to-supplement-your-nihongo-study">&lt;p&gt;Before coming to Japan, I had already studied Nihongo for over two years, albeit intermittently. I first studied at a language school in the Philippines, took 9 units of Japanese Language in college, and then took Saturday classes when I was already working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I wasn’t studying Nihongo continuously, I forgot a lot of the things I learned. When I was enrolling for the Saturday Nihongo classes, I had to take a level test, which I tried to cram for. I was evaluated to be one level lower than what I could have gotten if I had prepared for the exam. So much of my first days in class were a lessons I had already taken in college. The same thing happened when I came to Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When learning a language, exposure to the language is very important. Even now that I’m in Japan, I still look for ways I can supplement my language study. One of the things I turn to is technology; specifically, mobile and web applications.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dictionaries-辞書&quot;&gt;Dictionaries 辞書&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dictionaries listed below are English-Japanese dictionaries, but when you’re past N4 level, I recommend getting a Japanese-only dictionary. I haven’t exactly found one that I recommend yet, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;imiwa-ios&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/imiwa/id288499125?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;imiwa?&lt;/a&gt; (iOS)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when I was using an iPhone, this was my dictionary of choice. So far, I haven’t seen a dictionary app that can compare in terms of functionality, usability, and visual design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has definitions available in &lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;French&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Russian&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;German&lt;/strong&gt;. You can search in any of the mentioned languages, or in Japanese, romaji or otherwise. Aside form definitions, it also shows example sentences. Like most dictionary apps, you can search for Kanji by radical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I haven’t used this app in years, so I may not know or remember some other useful features.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;takaboto-android&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=jp.takoboto&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Takaboto&lt;/a&gt; (Android)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Takaboto is probably the closest dictionary app to &lt;em&gt;imiwa?&lt;/em&gt; that I’ve tried using on Android. It also has &lt;strong&gt;some&lt;/strong&gt; translations in French, German, and Russian. You can also search in Japanese or otherwise. There are also example sentences for &lt;strong&gt;some&lt;/strong&gt; words, although the example sentences don’t always show a variety of ways to use a particular word. The UI and Kanji search feature can definitely be improved though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about Takaboto is how it displays the Kanji’s stroke order. It shows the series of strokes at a glance and indicates at which point each stroke starts. You can also save words to &lt;a href=&quot;#ankidroid&quot;&gt;AnkiDroid&lt;/a&gt; to make your own deck, or add your own translation of a word (or phrase) in any language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jsho-android&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ric.Jsho&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Jsho&lt;/a&gt; (Android)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike &lt;em&gt;imiwa?&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Takaboto&lt;/em&gt;, Jsho doesn’t support languages other than English, nor does it display example sentences. You also have to toggle between English and Japanese when making a search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I do like about Jsho is that it stores your recent searches. There have been many times that I’ve used this feature, and it does save time, especially when I search for Kanji which I don’t know the reading of. Because it’s designed to be light-weight, it’s easier to see information at a glance. I tend to have more taps on &lt;em&gt;Takaboto&lt;/em&gt;, unless I have to keep switching between English and Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found it easier to search for Kanji by radical using Jsho, but I’m not sure if it’s just because I’ve been using it longer than &lt;em&gt;Takaboto&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of definitions, Takaboto and Jsho both use Jisho.org’s engine, so you’re going to see the same translations in both apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jishoorg&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jisho.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Jisho.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Jisho.org since I started formally studying Japanese. It now has a feature where you can draw the Kanji you want to search instead of just using radicals. It can also use voice input, though I haven’t tried using it yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from vocabulary, Jisho.org also has a database of common Japanese names, so if you don’t know how to read someone’s name, you can look it up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;translator&quot;&gt;Translator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;google-translate&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://translate.google.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Google Translate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When pressed for time or simply overwhelmed by unfamiliar Kanji or vocabulary, Google translate can be helpful. While not exactly accurate, it can be a starting point to translate text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s feature to translate text on an image can also save a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gamified-study-tools&quot;&gt;Gamified study tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These apps don’t particularly make learning Japanese any more fun, but they do come in handy when you have down time and you have nothing but your smartphone with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kanji-senpai&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=jp.rodriguez.kanjisenpai.android&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Kanji Senpai&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it’s name just says “Kanji”, it’s really more of a vocabulary tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kanji Senpai will help you learn Japanese vocabulary and kanji.
By using a spaced repetition system (SRS) you can memorize the different aspects of each vocabulary: meaning, pronunciation, reading, listening, writing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can choose from a vocabulary list, categorized by JLPT level. Each vocabulary will have the Kanji, kana, and English or Spanish translation. If you purchase a premium list, it will also include audio pronounciations and the hand-writing feature. The audio and hand-writing features also come with the free lists, but are very limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this useful in learning Kanji, but got bored with it after using it almost daily for about a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from using this app, I suggest looking for example sentences as well, so that when a word comes up, you can think of a simple sentence to use it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ankidroid&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;AnkiDroid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;em&gt;Kanji Senpai&lt;/em&gt;, this app also uses spaced repetition. However, this app is more of a self-assessment tool, whereas &lt;em&gt;Kanji Senpai&lt;/em&gt; is time-pressured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With AnkiDroid, you can make your own deck of ‘flashcards’, or download someone else’s. You can add images, notes, what-have-you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obenkyo&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.Obenkyo&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Obenkyo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obenkyo is sort of like a textbook turned into an app. It has grammar explanations, vocabulary and kanji lists, kana stroke order. It also has tests for kana, numbers, kanji, vocabulary, and particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UI can definitely be improved, but it is a very useful app to learn or review Nihongo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media&quot;&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are apps that help you retain information about grammar and vocabulary, the best way to practice a language is to use it to communicate with other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hellotalk&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.hellotalk&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;HelloTalk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HelloTalk is a social media platform for language learners. You can post “moments” with text and/or images; you can chat with or follow other people on HelloTalk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has translation and transliteration features. It can read out a body of text. It also allows you to mark a post as favorite, or correct someone’s spelling/grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading--news&quot;&gt;Reading / News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;nhk-news&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.clem.nhkradio&amp;amp;hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;NHK News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading news in simple Japanese not only keeps you informed about current events, but also expands your vocabulary, and familiarizes you with how to go about expressing information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After every article, there is a vocabulary list with descriptions in Japanese. There are also select vocabulary that you can click on to show a translation (English, Chinese, Korean). There’s also an audio reading of the article, and you can select the play speed. You can also play radio news on this app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you used any of this apps? Do you also find them helpful in learning Nihongo? Are there other apps that you could recommend? Share them in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Before coming to Japan, I had already studied Nihongo for over two years, albeit intermittently. I first studied at a language school in the Philippines, took 9 units of Japanese Language in college, and then took Saturday classes when I was already working. Because I wasn’t studying Nihongo continuously, I forgot a lot of the things I learned. When I was enrolling for the Saturday Nihongo classes, I had to take a level test, which I tried to cram for. I was evaluated to be one level lower than what I could have gotten if I had prepared for the exam. So much of my first days in class were a lessons I had already taken in college. The same thing happened when I came to Japan. When learning a language, exposure to the language is very important. Even now that I’m in Japan, I still look for ways I can supplement my language study. One of the things I turn to is technology; specifically, mobile and web applications.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should You Study Japanese in Japan?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/should-you-study-japanese-in-japan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should You Study Japanese in Japan?" /><published>2018-02-09T21:27:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-02-09T21:27:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/should-you-study-japanese-in-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/should-you-study-japanese-in-japan">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying Nihongo in Kyoto for about four months now, and throughout those four months I’ve had a lot of time to think about my decision to come here to study the language. I’ve made friends with different backgrounds and goals, and have recently had conversations with them about our current situation, studying Japanese in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you go to a language school in Japan, you assume that everyone who goes there is there because they &lt;strong&gt;want&lt;/strong&gt; to study Japanese. I think it’s unlikely that anyone here was forced to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before coming to Japan, I had this image, this expectation of what living in Japan would be like. It’s not that reality is actually so far from this expectation, but I did feel, almost immediately, disillusioned. 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That shouldn’t stop you from wanting to live and/or study in Japan, though. In fact, disillusionment would probably be good for you. It may not feel good at first, but it’s something you should come to terms with, and you shouldn’t let it stop you from accomplishing what you came to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-study-japanese-in-japan&quot;&gt;Why study Japanese in Japan?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are most likely Japanese language schools in your country as well, perhaps with the same intensity and methods as language schools here. So why come all the way here and spend so much to study Japanese?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exposure-to-the-language-and-the-culture&quot;&gt;Exposure to the language and the culture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I went to Seoul with my girlfriend. Months before our flight, I tried learning the Korean writing system. I didn’t exactly put a lot of effort into it, so of course I was only really able to retain information partially. But a few days into our stay, because I always tried to read the signs (and my girlfriend was always there to correct me) I was able to learn the writing system and actually retain the information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I even thought about studying Japanese here, I had already been taking Japanese classes almost every Saturday. I also had a day job at that time, and I found it difficult to keep motivated to study, and to make myself be exposed to the language more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I studied Japanese was at a Japanese language school in my hometown. In that language school, our teacher would, as much as possible, only use Nihongo while teaching. I found it to be very effective. I wanted that same experience, and take it to the next level. And here I am now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you come to Japan to study, you can’t not be exposed to the language and the culture. While there have been efforts to make Japan more foreigner-friendly, most people still prefer to speak in Japanese, and not all signs and public announcements have English translations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also situations where you have to speak in Japanese, no matter how bad you are at it. And if you make the most of your stay, you can immerse yourself in activities and situations that can enrich your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since language and culture are very much intertwined, being immersed in the culture helps rewire your brain to think in the language you are learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also a great sense of accomplishment when you start understanding things you encounter everyday, such as shop signs and announcements on public transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;travel-around-the-country&quot;&gt;Travel around the country&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During your free time, you can definitely go sight-seeing. If you have the money, you can take the Shinkansen and see other parts of the country. If not, you can still visit nearby prefectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4722/25741773198_394428f0d0_z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto shrine&quot; title=&quot;A man prays at a shrine in Kyoto&quot; class=&quot;post-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;make-international-friends&quot;&gt;Make international friends&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each language school has different demographics. Some schools have a lot of diversity, others tend to cater to a certain group of countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isi-education.com/location/kyoto/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;My school&lt;/a&gt; has a relatively large population of Chinese and Vietnamese students, but there are also a number of students from the Middle East and other Asian countries, Europe, and the Americas. &lt;em&gt;(I’m not entirely sure about the entire student body at this time. This is only from my observation.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have the opportunity to make friends with Japanese people. I don’t exactly have a Japanese friend yet, but some of the people I work with at my part-time job have been really friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-it-worth-it-to-study-japanese-in-japan&quot;&gt;Is it worth it to study Japanese in Japan?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying in Japan can be very expensive. Aside from school fees, there’s rent, transportation, health insurance, and food, among other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have (or your sponsor has) the money for it, if you get in a good school with good teachers, and if you make the most of your stay, I’d say that it is very much worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If money is going to be difficult, maybe consider other options. You may be able to work part-time in Japan, but you can’t be certain that you can immediately find a good job. In most cases, working part-time pays around JPY800 - JPY1,000 per hour. And if you plan on going to Japan with zero to little knowledge in Japanese, it’s going to be even harder to find a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can already have daily conversations in Japanese (JLPT N3), you will have more options in terms of the types of jobs that qualify for. It will also be easier to get a job wherein you can practice your Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you really want to study Japanese in Japan but don’t have enough for an entire term (which is usually three months long), you can go on a study trip instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a rough picture of the cost of living in Kyoto, I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-3-expenses&quot;&gt;my monthly expenses&lt;/a&gt; in a previous post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about studying Japanese in Japan, I wrote about the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-1-application&quot;&gt;application process&lt;/a&gt; and a little bit about &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto&quot;&gt;what it’s like to study at my current language school&lt;/a&gt; in previous posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Japan" /><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">I’ve been studying Nihongo in Kyoto for about four months now, and throughout those four months I’ve had a lot of time to think about my decision to come here to study the language. I’ve made friends with different backgrounds and goals, and have recently had conversations with them about our current situation, studying Japanese in Japan. When you go to a language school in Japan, you assume that everyone who goes there is there because they want to study Japanese. I think it’s unlikely that anyone here was forced to be here. Before coming to Japan, I had this image, this expectation of what living in Japan would be like. It’s not that reality is actually so far from this expectation, but I did feel, almost immediately, disillusioned.</summary></entry></feed>