<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-30T00:11:22+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Kim Tom Can</title><subtitle>Kim Tom Can - Online Portfolio. Web Design &amp; Development, Graphics Design.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part II: ISI Language School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part II: ISI Language School" /><published>2018-01-12T20:52:29+09:00</published><updated>2018-01-12T20:52:29+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isi-education.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;ISI Language School&lt;/a&gt; has campuses in Tokyo (Ikebukuro and Takedanobaba), Nagano, and Kyoto. The Kyoto campus just opened July 2017, and I started going there in October of the same year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Courses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At ISI, you can choose the course best suits your needs. In the Kyoto campus, as far as I know, there are two courses available: General and Academic.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;General Course&lt;/strong&gt;, the school plans cultural and tourist-y activities for the students as much as three times (if I’m not mistaken) every week. Classes are held in the morning, activities in the afternoon. Students are placed in different levels from Beginner to Intermediate. The screening criteria for placement aren’t as strict as in the Academic Course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not very familiar with the structure of the classes, but they are at a much slower pace than the academic course. Some of the students I met from the Basic level academic course said that they weren’t being taught grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;Academic Course&lt;/strong&gt;, which I am taking, are divided into three levels, subdivided into another two. These levels are Beginner (初級) I and II, Intermediate (中級) I and II, and Advanced (上級) I and II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Beginner I, almost all chapters in the Minna no Nihongo I textbook are covered. The coverage for Beginner II includes the last chapter/s in Minna no Nihongo that weren’t covered in Beginner I, plus most chapters of Minna no Nihongo II. (We were able to finish up to Chapter 46.) I didn’t take JLPT N5, but finishing Minna no Nihongo I should be enough to get you through N5; Minna no Nihongo II should be enough for N4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Intermediate I, after finishing Minna no Nihongo II, there is about a week or two of brushing up on nuances in the usage of particles, a few N3-level grammar, and then the curriculum jumps straight to N2 grammar. As far as I know, the school doesn’t really bother with N3. As to why, I’m not sure. The Kanji book we are using now is also for JLPT N2 preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Schedule (Academic Course)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginner and Intermediate I classes are held in the afternoon, while Intermediate II and Advanced classes are held in the morning. I started at Beginner II. Everyday we learn six new Kanji, which we have to memorize for a 10-item multiple choice test the following day. Every two days we learn a new chapter from Minna no Nihongo, grammar and vocabulary; and every couple of weeks we have a long test about the grammar and vocabulary from three chapters of the book. Everyday, we have homework. We spend 3.5 hours in class, with three 10-minute breaks every 45 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our class had three different teachers, each assigned 1-2 days a week for our class. So for Mondays we had Teacher A; Tuesdays and Fridays Teacher B; and Wednesdays and Thursdays, Teacher C. In the Beginner I class, I think they had a different teacher for each day of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Support&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The school helps you get a name stamp (判子 or 印鑑), open a bank account, and maybe find a part-time job (though perhaps not the one you’re looking for, if you’re picky). You can ask your teachers for help with things like filling out forms, how to go to a certain place, how to get a commuter pass (&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: You can’t get a STUDENT commuter pass as an ISI Language School student), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dormitories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ISI Kyoto has three dormitories. Two of them are in Arashiyama; one is in Kameoka. I don’t think the dorms are actually owned by ISI. It seems to me they are only partnered with housing companies that own and manage these dorms. That said, there are teachers assigned to coordinate with these companies, so that if you do have concerns, you can approach the teacher in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I have more to say about the dormitories, which I will write in a separate blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
The General Course is more expensive than the Academic Course. Some students transferred from General Course to Academic Course because they wanted to learn the language more in depth. The school doesn’t give refunds, so it would be best to think about which course best suits your objectives. Hopefully this helps you make that choice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read about the application procedure for language schools in Japan, check out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-1-application&quot;&gt;Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part I: Application&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part III will be a review of ISI Kyoto.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="isi" /><summary type="html">ISI Language School has campuses in Tokyo (Ikebukuro and Takedanobaba), Nagano, and Kyoto. The Kyoto campus just opened July 2017, and I started going there in October of the same year. Courses At ISI, you can choose the course best suits your needs. In the Kyoto campus, as far as I know, there are two courses available: General and Academic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part I: Application</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-1-application" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part I: Application" /><published>2018-01-07T20:52:29+09:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T20:52:29+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-1-application</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/studying-japanese-in-kyoto-part-1-application">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been studying Japanese in Kyoto since October, and I’ve been meaning to write about the process because when I was looking into studying at a language school in Japan, I just couldn’t seem to find enough resources online, and that made me feel really anxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to write about this topic in three parts: the first being about applications; the second about my school and school life; and the third, a review of the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first considered studying at a Japanese language school in Japan when my girlfriend’s friend started going to one herself. At that time I was back in the Philippines taking Japanese lessons every Saturday, but was feeling largely unsatisfied with the pace of the lessons (which is not to say that I was the most diligent student, because I wasn’t). Going to class only once a week, it was hard for me to retain all the vocabulary and kanji we learned in class. I felt that if I wanted to become fluent in Japanese, I had to put myself in a situation where I would always encounter the language and be forced to think and communicate in that language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Primary Research&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend’s friend made her application via an organization called Jellyfish Education, which she complained about, so I didn’t consider approaching them (but in retrospect maybe I should have). It’s not that it’s a bogus organization, but I didn’t bother looking into her complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started looking at Japanese language schools on the Internet, and then I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://gogonihon.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Go! Go! Nihon&lt;/a&gt;, which is a free service that helps foreigners study Japanese in Japan. They had a list of language schools on their website, rating each school by the level of difficulty of the school’s approach to teaching Japanese. They also have information about tuition fees, facilities, and other points with which you can compare one school with another. I was able to choose which school I was most interested in, and filled up a form on the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In choosing your school (or if you really want to study at a Japanese language school in Japan), I highly suggest looking into how classes are conducted, what to expect from the school, and what the school expects from its students. You don’t want to waste money on a school only to find out that it doesn’t fit your learning style. Keep in mind also the culture of education in Japan. Some people get frustrated with school and end up having an unpleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications for Japanese language schools generally start about than six months before your entry month. The specific documents you will need for your application should be on the school’s website, but the most notable requirement, I think, is money. You should be able to prove to the school that you have enough money to pay for your school as well as living expenses during your stay. If you don’t personally have that amount of money, you should have a sponsor who is willing to support you financially during your study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Direct Application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t actually need an organization to help you with your application to the school, although they can make it a little more convenient. Because that’s what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there was a misunderstanding in my email correspondence with Go! Go! Nihon, so instead of pointing that out right away, I just tried directly applying to the school that I initially wanted to apply to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things were going great. I was able to submit the requirements, and then it was time to pay for the application fee. My bank was asking for an invoice or some proof of the reason for the transaction because of whatever policy they have, so I tried sending the money via Western Union instead as it seemed less of a hassle to do. Turns out the transaction failed, so I ran back into Go! Go! Nihon’s open arms and here I am now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Go! Go! Nihon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people you talk to on Go! Go! Nihon were or still are language school students, so they know what people have to go through to study Japanese in Japan. The thing is, they make mistakes, too. When they do, just send them back an email and clarify things. They’re nice people and will own up to their mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying through Go! Go! Nihon also has perks, like special discounts and access to a community of fellow Japanese language learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview of the Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #339966;&quot;&gt;APPLICANT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;] Submit requirements and pay application fee.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3366ff;&quot;&gt;SCHOOL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;] Approve your application and submit to Japanese Immigration.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;JPN IMMIGRATION&lt;/strong&gt;] Issue Certificate of Eligibility.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3366ff;&quot;&gt;SCHOOL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;] Issue invoice for tuition and other fees.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;span style=&quot;color: #339966;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;APPLICANT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;] Pay fees.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3366ff;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SCHOOL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;] Send you your Certificate of Eligibility (CoE).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #339966;&quot;&gt;APPLICANT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;] Apply for Visa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the school submits your application to Immigration, you will have to wait about a month for news if your CoE was granted or not. You will know the results about a month before school starts. Depending on your school, you may have to pay for your school fees before they mail you your CoE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I had to pay for the first 6 months of school, and the first 3 months rent for the dorm. After the school confirmed receipt of my payment, they sent my CoE within 48hrs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you receive your CoE, start applying for your visa. In the Philippines, language school students need to apply for their visa via an accredited travel agency listed in the Japan Embassy’s website. I was able to get mine in less than a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Warning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do be careful in choosing which language school to enroll in. There are some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2017/01/03/national/social-issues/experts-warn-japans-language-schools-are-becoming-a-front-for-importing-cheap-labor/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; class=&quot;external&quot;&gt;shady language schools&lt;/a&gt; out there that exploit the influx of foreigners coming to Japan to learn Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read about the what it’s like to study at ISI Kyoto, check out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/studying-in-japanese-in-kyoto-part-2-isi-kyoto&quot;&gt;Studying Japanese in Kyoto - Part II: ISI Kyoto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="language" /><category term="study" /><category term="Nihongo" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="life" /><category term="application" /><summary type="html">I’ve been studying Japanese in Kyoto since October, and I’ve been meaning to write about the process because when I was looking into studying at a language school in Japan, I just couldn’t seem to find enough resources online, and that made me feel really anxious. I’m going to write about this topic in three parts: the first being about applications; the second about my school and school life; and the third, a review of the school. I first considered studying at a Japanese language school in Japan when my girlfriend’s friend started going to one herself. At that time I was back in the Philippines taking Japanese lessons every Saturday, but was feeling largely unsatisfied with the pace of the lessons (which is not to say that I was the most diligent student, because I wasn’t). Going to class only once a week, it was hard for me to retain all the vocabulary and kanji we learned in class. I felt that if I wanted to become fluent in Japanese, I had to put myself in a situation where I would always encounter the language and be forced to think and communicate in that language.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DOST and NBI Clearance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/clearance-dost-nbi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DOST and NBI Clearance" /><published>2015-09-20T21:52:29+09:00</published><updated>2015-09-20T21:52:29+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/clearance-dost-nbi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2015/clearance-dost-nbi">&lt;p&gt;Datapuwa't isa sa mga pinaka-ayaw kong gawin ay ang pag-aasikaso ng mga dokumento, lalo na sa mga ahensiya ng gobyerno, wala akong magawa kundi gawin ito dahil rekisito ito sa trabaho. Hindi naman ako puwedeng (at ayaw ko naman na) habambuhay humingi ng pera sa magulang ko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naisipan kong isalaysay ang karanasan ko sa pagkat pakiramdam ko'y hindi sapat ang mga nabasa ko sa Internet tungkol sa pagpoproseso ng DOST Final Clearance at NBI Clearance para sa mga tulad ko. O siguro'y di ko lang lubusang nahalungkat ang mga message boards at blogs para makakalap ng sapat na impormasyon para mapanatag ako. Marami rin sa mga nabasa ko'y nakasulat sa Ingles; nais ko namang magbahagi ng alternatibong babasahin para sa mga mas komportableng magbasa ng Tagalog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Ang Kalbaryo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isa akong dating DOST-SEI Merit scholar. Noong ikatlong taon ko sa unibersidad ay lumipat ako sa kursong hindi nakalista bilang priority course ng DOST-SEI. Ito ang dahilan kung bakit natigil (terminated) ang aking scholarship. Nagpadala ako ng email sa seischolarships@gmail.com (dahil na rin hindi ako matulungan ng mga nasa Regional Office sa La Trinidad) tungkol sa pagkuha ng Final Clearance ko subalit wala talaga silang naitulong sa akin. Pinagpaliban ko muna ito.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kinailangan kong kumuha ng NBI Clearance para sa trabaho. Nagpasiya akong sa Baguio kumuha ng NBI Clearance dahil palagay ko'y di ko kakailanganing pumila nang kehaba-haba o ketagal-tagal doon. Di ko akalaing magkakaroon ako ng HIT dahil hindi naman ako kriminal, hindi rin naman pangkaraniwan ang pangalan ko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinagpaliban ko muna ulit ang NBI Clearance. Mabuti at hindi naman ako kinukulit ng HR namin tungkol dito. Wala pa rin kasi akong Vacation Leave bilang probationary pa lang ako sa kumpanya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Di naglaon ay kinailangan ko na ring kumuha ng clearance (para sa ibang bagay). Semi-flexi ang oras namin sa trabaho, kung kaya karamihan ng pag-asikaso ko ng mga dokumentong ito ay nangyari sa umaga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Una, nag-apply ako online para sa NBI Clearance. Sa Ortigas Center ako nagtatrabaho, kaya sa tanggapan ng NBI sa Robinson's Galleria ako nagpunta. Sandali lang ang proseso noong dumaan ako (online na rin ako nagbayad) bandang 6PM. May hit kaya pinabalik ako sa ibang araw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pagkabalik ko, sinabihan akong pumunta sa Main Office ng NBI para sa Quality Control Interview. Sabi noong kuya sa tanggapan ay meron akong dalawang (2) linggo para asikasuhin ang Quality Control Interview. Agahan ko raw dahil ang unang 300 aplikante lamang ang tatanggapin. Tinanong niya kung iskolar ako, at sinabihan akong dalhin ang clearance ng scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nasa DOST-SEI website ang tungkol sa mga clearance na maaaring ipag-apply. Maaari na ring mag-download at print ng application form, mayroon din namang makukuha sa mismong tanggapan ng DOST-SEI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wala pang alas-otso ay nasa opisina na ako ng DOST-SEI, sa pangambang kakailanganin ko pang pumila. Halos wala namang ibang tao pagkarating ko. May isa lang akong nakasabay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sinabihan ako na para makuha ang DOST-SEI clearance na kakailanganin para sa NBI Clearance ay kailangan munang bayaran nang bahagya ang i-rerefund sa DOST gawa ng pagkatigil ng scholarship ko. Binigyan ako ng estimate ng kailangang bayaran. Bumalik ako kinabukasan (Biyernes) para bayaran ito(nang buo, para makuha na rin ang final Clearance). Pinabalik ako ng Lunes ng hapon, pero Martes ng umaga na ako dumaan para kunin na sa wakas ang DOST Clearance. Kabilang na rito ang clearance na para sa NBI at Immigration (para makabiyahe palabas ng bansa). Sa tatlong araw na dumaan ako sa DOST, wala pang 15 minuto kada araw ay tapos na ang mga kinailangang asikasuhin. Nakaabot naman ako sa opisina bago mag-10:00 ng umaga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susunod ay ang NBI. Alas-7 ng umaga ako dumating sa Main Office ng NBI at may pila na para sa Quality Control (QC). Ang sabi sa mga nabasa ko sa Internet ay alas-8 nagsisimula ang QC Interview, subalit ang nakapaskil sa opisina ng NBI ay alas-7 ito nagsisimula. May isang oras din akong naghintay bago ako tinawag. Dahil scholarship lang naman ang rason ng pagka-HIT ko, binigay ko lamang ang clearance mula sa DOST, pinapirma ako sa clearance, at pinapunta na sa Releasing ng NBI Clearance. Wala pang 8:30n.u. ay natapos na ako sa NBI (at muling nakabalik sa opisina bago mag-alas 10n.u.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Mga Bumagabag sa Akin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May ilang bagay na bumagabag sa akin. Akala ko may kinalaman ang HIT ko sa 1) katukayo; 2) isang kaso kung saan ako ang biktima; o 3) iyong di ko nabayaran o maayos na napa-terminate ang subskripsyon sa Globe dahil sa #2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nabasa kong hindi ikinokonsidera ang civil cases (kasong sibil) sa pagkakaroon ng HIT, mga kasong kriminal lamang. Kung kaya napanatag din ako sa #3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ang nagpakaba na lamang sa akin ay ang #1 at #2. Kung sakaling may HIT pa maliban sa scholarship, kailan pa makukuha ang clearance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sa kabutihang palad, wala namang naging problema doon. May nakita rin akong nagtatanong tungkol sa pagkakaroon ng HIT kung ikaw ang nagsampa ng kaso. Hindi ko alam kung magkakaroon ng HIT kung hindi pa sarado ang kaso, pero kung tapos naman na ito, mukhang hindi ito kailangang problemahin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahit papaano, kaya namang makuha nang mabilisan ang mga dokumento mula sa gobyerno, lalo na kung napaghandaan mo ang mga ito bago pumunta sa mga tanggapan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="adulting" /><category term="Philippines" /><category term="documents" /><category term="NBI" /><category term="DOST" /><category term="clearance" /><summary type="html">Datapuwa't isa sa mga pinaka-ayaw kong gawin ay ang pag-aasikaso ng mga dokumento, lalo na sa mga ahensiya ng gobyerno, wala akong magawa kundi gawin ito dahil rekisito ito sa trabaho. Hindi naman ako puwedeng (at ayaw ko naman na) habambuhay humingi ng pera sa magulang ko. Naisipan kong isalaysay ang karanasan ko sa pagkat pakiramdam ko'y hindi sapat ang mga nabasa ko sa Internet tungkol sa pagpoproseso ng DOST Final Clearance at NBI Clearance para sa mga tulad ko. O siguro'y di ko lang lubusang nahalungkat ang mga message boards at blogs para makakalap ng sapat na impormasyon para mapanatag ako. Marami rin sa mga nabasa ko'y nakasulat sa Ingles; nais ko namang magbahagi ng alternatibong babasahin para sa mga mas komportableng magbasa ng Tagalog.</summary></entry></feed>